All right.
We were talking about he says
the third level of ethics of the
perfection of morality
is called
which means
morality or ethics which helps other
people, okay? So that's the third level
of ethics, okay?
is
the second one.
Making good karma, making more good
karma, okay? First one is
it means avoid hurting people. Avoid
hurting people first morality.
Second
make good karma with your morality.
Third
We got to cut the sound on this.
I'm hearing this old man talking.
This is me.
Okay, and
means take care of other take care of
take care of the world, okay? It's the
third level of morality, okay? Take care
of the world. Then he says
if you want an example, we can say do
she
okay? Say say do a
do a ma pa
she
do a
ma pa she
These are four ways to treat your
students.
Okay, these are four ways to treat your
students and this is the highest kind of
morality. It's very interesting.
Treating your students well
is the highest kind of morality, okay?
And here's the four ways, okay? It's
called four ways. The name in the
ancient language is
four ways to bring your students
together. Four ways to bring bring your
students together, okay? First one
and I it's not in the book, so I got it
from another book for you, okay?
And this is one by Jetsun Kunga, okay?
This is called the Ocean of Reasoning.
It's a commentary on
Nagarjuna.
If there was an old man who spent 12
years translating
some Kunga's commentary to Chandrakirti,
and if he didn't have anything else to
do,
he could do 12 years on this book,
which is my secret plan.
Okay?
It will be 3,000 pages or something,
okay? And he says, here it is, okay?
Uh
Jimba means
uh
attract your students with your
generosity, okay? Take Give them $100
for a small answer.
Okay? And just be super generous to your
students, okay? Always uh
feed them, overfeed them.
Uh
you know, my teacher was very good at
that. That's That's how he got me to
come.
Uh
always, you know,
say come talk.
Say len talk.
Come talk.
Len talk.
Come talk means the student come for the
class, and it's a dry class. Come combo
means dry. It means no refreshment.
Len talk means wet class.
And And that means there's good
refreshments. Is this a len talk or a
come talk, Tim? I
Anyway,
uh
you should So, attract your students by
being super generous, okay? Be Be super
generous to your student. And I learned
it from my teacher.
And you know,
we buy houses, we buy
cars, we have a friend
uh doctor were very good to do that he's
very generous help your students
uh whatever they need help them, you
know, it's
that's the
first
of the four types of higher morality,
okay? Take care of your students and
attract them whatever they like.
Study your student and find out what
they like, okay? What they like to
drink, what they like to eat,
what they like to do,
study them.
They should be like your long room.
Your student is your long room.
You should study your student
and see what do they like and then
attract them like the bee to the honey.
What was how that go? What did the bee
say?
Oh, what did the sushi say to the bee?
What's up, bee?
Okay, I'll give you a commission.
All right, what's up, bee? Uh
okay, so
No, you got to say, "What's up, bee?"
Okay.
Uh so first find out what your student
enjoy and and give it to them. And by
the way, you can go broke, okay?
I went broke many times. Here we were
talking uh
in New York when when I started ACI. Uh
I I went broke many times.
I was $30,000 in debt,
which would nowadays like $100,000 when
I finished the Diamond Way course
cuz I pay for everything and and I
remember I went
I left Diamond Mountain with huge debt.
It took me several years to pay the debt
just because I feed everybody, make
everybody happy.
Okay, so
don't be cheap. Don't worry about it.
Karma will come back, okay? It takes a
little while.
Karma doesn't ripen in one day, okay?
But you will never
lose money if you support your students,
okay? You will always be
happy. You will always be wealthy.
You will always be comfortable, okay?
Take care of your students.
If you have to spend money, spend money,
okay? And you don't have to worry about
it. Just do it. Shut up and do it.
Okay? Take care of your students. And
whatever they need, take care of them,
okay?
Uh
it's very very fun.
All Buddhism is fun. I think it should
be called funnism
and not Buddhism, okay? If you really
understand Buddhism it's a lot of fun.
It's like party all day.
Okay.
Second
over praise your students.
Okay. Oh, you so smart. I never had a
student like that. You know,
and like that, okay?
Wow.
You actually helped one old grandma. You
a bodhisattva. You must be a
bodhisattva.
You know, like that. Like everything
they do
it's like having your kid, right?
Yeah, it's like having your kid.
Uh just
super Every mom praise their kid, right?
Like crazy.
You know, just say wow, you so you the
smartest kid in the whole city.
I don't know how
your mom so lucky to have you, you know,
like that. Okay?
So,
and by the way, don't lie, okay?
Just
make it extra
a little bit and encourage them.
Encourage your student, okay? Be be be
happy. Have fun.
And any little good thing they do, say,
"God, you're so smart." You know, then
they make 10 mistakes, don't say
anything.
Okay? It's just like having a
You're okay.
We were with Sophie Chao
uh
during the break and she does this to
her her daughter. I I watched it, you
know.
Encourage them, okay? Encourage them.
Yes, they do 10 things wrong every time
they do one good thing.
But if you talk about the 10 bad things,
they don't improve and and they don't
feel happy, okay? Wait. Sometimes you
have to wait a long time
for the student to do something correct.
Then you say, "Wow, you're so my best
student. I can't believe it, you know,
you okay?" So,
be encouraging. This is Buddhism, okay?
This is real Buddhism, okay? Be generous
with your students. If you go broke with
your students, you're a good teacher.
Okay? I I many times
even today,
that bag is completely empty. I want to
give $10 to the maid in my room and I'm
like, "Oops, I gave all the money away."
Okay? And then secondly,
uh
encourage them. Don't don't look for
their mistakes.
It's the same as children, you know,
like Korean.
So, just encourage everything every time
they do something good,
uh
tell them, "Wow, you're you're the best
kid in
Kuala Lumpur or something.
JB not this, okay? Johor Johor Bahru.
I thought JB was the director of A O L.
No, okay. Number one. Third one. Say
uh
don't chepa.
Yeah, don't chepa means
do not tolerate it.
If your students
uh don't
don't do what they say.
Okay? Uh don't encourage them
to really do something, okay? Don't let
them be lazy, okay? Don't chepa means
it's not enough to have a long mean
class
and you teach for 14 years
and the student don't do anything.
Okay? Then you're not a good teacher,
okay? So, educate
your students in Buddhism
but then uh make sure they do something,
okay?
That's a big difference, right?
Uh
we are not trying to create uh Buddhist
scholars.
We are trying to create Buddhist people.
Uh
so, make sure they
do it, okay? And every time they do
something, say wow, that's just great,
okay? Get them to
do their Buddhism in their life and not
in their mouth, okay? Understand?
Okay. Number four.
Most difficult. $100.
Well, well, I you're the teacher.
This lady.
Easy.
Number four. Wow.
How many people?
Uh to be an example.
Yeah, great. Okay, $100.
Yeah.
Watch the appropriate idioms, strangely
enough.
You could say walk the talk, practice
what you preach.
Okay? Like as a teacher,
uh
the highest morality of a teacher
is to do what you talk.
Okay? The highest morality of a teacher
is to do what you talk. And by the way,
just as a personal
advice,
to be a teacher
and to not follow what you are talking
is schizophrenia. It's very
uncomfortable.
Uh it will make you crazy. You will go
crazy, you know? You You Like you get up
in the class and you say,
"Everyone should
do the good night book. You should put
your electronics away at 10:00 p.m." If
you don't do it yourself,
then then really I think you become uh
schizophrenic. You You You become a
little bit crazy.
Okay? It's not healthy
to teach Buddhism
if you're not doing it yourself. Okay?
You will go You will be unhappy. You'll
be more unhappy.
Okay? Uh it's it's very uncom- I can
tell you
cuz it it happened to me in my life. If
you are not following
what you are teaching,
it it's very uncomfortable, okay? And
you feel
You feel dirty. You feel really dirty,
okay? So, number four, highest
advice for teacher,
you know, do what you talk about. And
And if if you can't do it, then shut up
and
go do it and then talk about it.
Okay?
And it's not easy. Uh it's not easy,
okay?
Uh
but I can as a old man advice,
old teacher advice
Keep working on yourself. Never give up
on yourself. Keep Keep trying to follow
what you teach.
Never be satisfied.
You know, never give up. You say, "Oh, I
can't do that, you know. I I
I'm teaching them
to put away their electronics, but
secretly I I get my phone out every
night and I watch bad things, you know."
It's
It will make you crazy, okay? So, try to
Try to stop it, okay? Try to do what you
teach.
And And I'll tell you something, okay?
As a teacher
And by the way, I do do what I teach so
far.
But But what I'm saying is if you if you
don't do it if if you have secrets and
you don't want your student to know
you're you're not following your own
teaching.
It's It's a very uncomfortable and
the student can smell it. They can smell
it, okay? They They can feel it, okay?
They
You know, you say "Oh, 10:00, you should
put away your phone. Don't watch the
dirty thing after 10:00, you know." Like
try and then the student's like
Something uncomfortable here. They can
tell, okay? You
You cannot
Nobody's a perfect liar.
Okay? You make all these kind of
subconscious
expressions and you don't move
naturally. When you're not telling the
truth as a teacher
everybody knows, okay? I'm sorry.
Okay?
It's
So, on one side
the teacher who don't want to change
they become more and more
skillful to hide their mistakes.
On the other hand
it just fixed the god damn mistake.
And don't do it anymore.
And then everyone's happy. Okay? Then
you can get up proud. You can say, "I
give my computer to Rob every night at
10:00. I I didn't look at that computer
after 10:00 for 1 year since I started."
And you can smell
that the teacher is telling the truth.
Okay? And you can smell when they're not
telling the truth.
So,
don't try to hide something. Just clean
it up.
You know, don't
You can not let your mom see your dirty
bedroom,
or you can clean it up.
And it's easier to clean it up. Okay?
Got it? So, a teacher has to be
we have to have integrity. We have to do
what we say.
And it's We're not perfect.
And we will make mistakes. And And I'm
not saying you should quit teaching.
I'm saying you should clean up a little
bit more every day. Okay? Get better and
better. Okay?
Nobody's perfect teacher. No teacher is
perfect except my teacher. Uh
But I'm just saying uh
We all make mistakes. And be honest.
Okay? If If you stand up and you say,
"I'm a teacher. I'm a Buddhist teacher.
I made this mistake. I had an abortion,
for example, when I was young, very
young."
You know, and I'm honest. I tell people.
I don't try to hide either.
Like that. Just be honest. People can
smell.
And then you you're a better teacher.
You will be a better The teacher who
makes mistakes is better than the
teacher who pretend not to make
mistakes.
Okay? Got it?
All right.
Next one.
Uh then I yawn then cheater.
now he has a interesting list. It's 11
different ways
that you can help your students. Okay,
there's 11 different suggestions
of ways that you can help your students.
Okay, number one
uh
help people with things they have
to do work for your work hard for your
students.
And when your students have trouble
show up.
Okay.
Be there. You can I have a student who's
uh
got cancer problem right now, you know.
And uh
and we me and my wife we we invite them
over frequently, much more than before.
And show up means
be there for them. Okay, be there.
Help them.
Talk chepa means uh
be there to share their trouble.
Okay, be there for people. Okay, now
if you have 138,000 students
uh
okay
uh you cannot answer every email. It's
not possible. I have 50,000 emails
waiting. Okay, and
you know, don't go crazy. Okay, but as
much as you can be there
for them. Okay, if you cannot be there
try to find someone who can be there for
you. Okay, like that. All right, but
take care of your students.
Number two
uh pay special attention to people who
don't know how to do something that
they're supposed to be doing.
If you have a cafe
in a small town
and the manager doesn't know how to make
money apparently
and lose your money every day
then teach them, okay? Then
politely, happily
take them to, you know
another restaurant
give them dinner and say, "Look, you
know uh it seems like you don't know how
to
do the finance."
And they say, "Yeah, I don't know how."
Then help them, okay? So, there's a
special karma of helping people learn to
do something that they don't know how to
do.
Okay, that's a special kind of karma.
Okay, number three, "Can dog pay?"
"Then chepa."
Always repay kindness that someone
showed you. Someone helped you as a
teacher
then then
repay the kindness, okay? Like don't
just say, "Oh, thanks for the donation.
See you next year."
Okay, like
think about it and and show your
gratitude.
And
and help them also, okay?
Uh number four
if you see someone who has depression or
fear
then slow down, take special time to
help them, okay?
Or
if you have 138,000
students
then arrange help for them. Find someone
who can help them, okay? Who's someone
who's
frightened when they have some problem
in their life, okay?
All right,
uh number five
"Young and key serenade don't chepa."
Uh especially people who had a loss in
their life. They lost their family
member
or they they lost their finance
or they lost their house or they lost
their good health
then
especially pay attention to those people
who are sad. Something happened in their
life and they are sad. Okay, nyang en
means shock shoka
in in Sanskrit. Ashoka Ashoka means the
king who had no grief.
Okay, so
uh
if someone is suffering this way, they
lost their family members they special
attention. Okay, as a teacher
especially. Okay.
Long list of things the teacher has to
do. The teacher will be too busy. The
teacher won't get enough sleep. The
teacher will be grumpy and break their
own morality.
So teacher's responsibility
get everything done and rest
at the same time.
Okay, real teacher has to learn, right?
Okay,
pom be den chepa pay special attention
to poor people.
Okay, pay special attention to poor
people. People lost their country. We
have Ukrainian friends we brought from
Ukraine.
My wife and I sponsored several.
And it's hard. It's difficult. It's a
lot of money.
And uh
but we really enjoy it and it turns out
they make us very happy. They they
they're very
we have a really good time with them
they are doing wonderful
work in in our
community. Okay.
All right,
seven ne chawa de be den chepa.
There's a special karma of a teacher to
make sure that the students or pay
attention to people who do not have a
place to stay.
That's called ne chawa. Okay, ne chawa
means uh
For example, someone's building their
house
or someone's repairing their house,
someone lost their home in a war or
something,
then pay special attention
as a teacher especially.
And every
animal
in this world
should have their little hole
where they go.
Right?
Human being animal or mouse
animal,
they should have a little place to go,
which is their home.
And if you find an animal
or you find a student who doesn't have a
place, in English we say they don't have
a place to call their home,
then help them get this place. That's a
special karma of a teacher. Okay? Make
sure you help people
find a home.
And it applies to uh
animals. We We just adopted a cat last
week.
She kissed me.
She's a little bit wild.
We're getting to know each other.
Okay, so homeless people people homeless
animals,
special attention.
Uh Lotim Badubi Dinchepa, if people are
having fights in their group or their
marriage or or anything else between
companies,
then as a teacher, as a Buddhist teach
who's learning the perfection of
morality,
pay special attention to bringing people
back together, people who having
conflict.
Then a Buddhist
has a sensitive nose.
Okay? I don't have a sensitive nose. My
wife has to say, "You didn't change your
shirt for 2 weeks."
I'm like,
"I don't smell anything." She said,
"Your nose doesn't work."
It's interesting cuz if she
makes a cake or something, I can smell
it um immediately.
But, if I have to change my pants, she's
like
She's like, "Can't you just wash your
pants?" Okay, so anyway,
uh
A Buddhist has to have a good nose for
trouble.
And if you're in a group, uh especially
a Buddhist group,
and there's some people don't get along
with each other, or some husband and
wife not getting along with each other,
or
you know, then a
a Buddhist will do something. A Buddhist
will not watch it.
They will try to do something. They will
try to help.
They'll try to Oh, this group, these two
people don't like each other.
Then they will try to help, okay?
Whether you succeed or not is not the
question.
Okay? Like Like if a couple's not
getting along,
and the husband fight with the wife, and
the wife fight with the husband, you
have to try
your best to help them. But,
you cannot fix their karma, okay? You
cannot fix their karma. Some people
just have karma to make each other
miserable for year after year after
year,
you know, and they have good teachers,
uh but they they can't fix it, okay? You
You cannot fix
other people's problems.
But, you have to try.
There's a difference, right? Understand?
It's a difference. As a teacher,
especially,
your responsibility is to try.
But, their karma is their karma. You
cannot fix their karma, okay? They have
to
Only they can fix their karma. If else
could fix your karma, there would be no
dead people in this world.
Because Buddha has already been here.
Buddha was already here.
And he did a good job.
People still dying, okay? Buddha could
not stop it. People still getting
divorced. People Buddha could not stop
it. You think you can stop it?
So, do your best.
Try to help.
That's your responsibility. Don't get
discouraged if if it doesn't work, okay?
You try try try.
And these people still get divorced. You
try try try.
These people still fighting inside the
Buddhist group.
And okay.
Then smile.
Try again tomorrow, okay? That's all you
can do, okay? Buddha couldn't fix them.
You you do your best.
But don't go crazy, okay? Do your best.
Take interest.
Oh, you seem guys It seems like you guys
are having trouble. Yeah, can I help?
No. Okay.
I mean,
uh Yonge Boulevard should be doing
shamatha.
If you see somebody doing something
cool, step in and help them, okay? Wow,
I like that project you guys are doing.
Marie Kondo.
Uh
I never you know, I didn't know about
this lady. I have a friend, Angeli. Some
you guys know her.
Sometimes I ask her to come to my house
and help clean my house. Me and my wife
ask her to come and she went there last
night and help clean the house. She cut
the tombstone rose.
Because it's going to take over the
whole house.
And and she cut this special rose, you
know? And uh so she's
she's like uh
China help us. And she said, "Geshe la,
your Your is
Everything's confused. You need to
make your house neater.
Then you can find the things you're
looking for, you know.
And you're like you also feel happier if
your house is neater.
I have a book for you.
You know, and she gave me this book.
It's by Marie Kondo. She's Japanese
woman.
It's how to straighten up your house.
I will never do it.
But my friend who I hired to straighten
up my She came and she straightened up
everything. I can't find anything.
You know.
But then she said here I There's a card.
She made a card.
This is over here. This is She made a
map of my house.
And I actually use it pretty frequently.
I'm like, where in the hell is the
And uh
So she read this book. There's a Netflix
series by Marie Kondo. So uh I have the
honor
to give a talk with her this week.
Then it What day?
There you go.
I really appreciate who made the old
picture of Geshe la.
Looks so young.
Have lots of hair.
Uh
but anyway, uh you know, you're very
welcome to come if you'd like to come.
We did a program together before and
she's very cool and we really enjoy each
other. Yeah. We're doing advertisement
for Marie Kondo.
Yeah, I'd like to thank Sophie Chauveau
for making it happen, you know.
Okay.
Uh
anyway, if someone's doing something
right,
if someone's helping many people, then
give them some support, okay? It's one
thing to help people
who are
their house is getting bombed in a war.
That's important. But, also
if you see someone doing something cool,
then make a donation or or help them.
Do Do you need some help? I like what
you're doing. What you're doing is cool.
And and I want to help, okay? And then
give them some help, okay?
Lopashubedenchipam means
if you see the opposite,
if you see people going to get
themselves in trouble,
then say say something or do something.
And And I'm I'm a strange
personality, my wife told me.
Uh
I don't like to upset other people, you
know? So,
some person will do something wrong,
and I I won't say anything.
Then they'll do something worse, and I
won't say anything. Then they get in big
trouble. Still, I won't say anything.
And my wife said that's not kindness.
You should say something. If someone's
doing something wrong,
uh you know, every human being
doesn't
matter you're Buddhist teacher or or
you're Buddhist, it doesn't matter.
Every human being,
if you see someone doing something that
will hurt them
or hurt other people, then you should
say something. You should do something,
you know? Uh you should
get involved.
Okay? Don't be afraid to get involved,
okay? Uh
not over involved, right? Not nosy.
But, if someone's going to hurt
themselves or they're going to hurt
somebody else,
then you you know,
politely you can say something, okay?
All right. Um
that's number 10. Number 11, Zudukedun.
Dutukee
Denchipaten number 22 Yulor. Number
is when the time comes to do a miracle
to help other people, you must do it.
Okay?
Like fly in the sky or
pick up a car with one finger
or pay your bills early.
Other miracles.
Right?
Okay?
Uh
and then he has a commentary, it's very
cute. He says day number names
farmer two near long rain new bacon at
day. We can do all of these except
number 11.
So he kind of he says this list
is an old Buddhist list.
It has 11 parts. Number 11, if you can't
do it yet, don't get worried. Don't
worry about it. You can let it go for
now.
But just remember,
when the day comes that you can fly in
the sky
or you can pick up a building with your
little finger,
if it will help somebody, you have a
responsibility to do it to do it, okay?
If you are capable
to do a miracle,
then you should do it. You you have a
responsibility to do it when the time
comes. When it's the right time. Not
just to show off.
Something like that, okay?
All right, don't know
pay
my cousin
told by him.
All forms of helping other people are
included into the third type of
morality, okay? Which is don't you too.
Uh helping other people, okay? That's So
it's interesting in English, in America,
morality means no killing, no stealing,
no lying.
In Buddhism,
doing nice things for other people is a
second level of morality.
And
doing ultimately nice things for other
people
is the highest level of morality, you
know, get them to meditate. Get them to
think about emptiness, okay? That's a
higher kind of morality, okay?
All right.
Even if you're not in the mood to take
Buddhist vows, at least learn the 10
good deeds and don't hurt people, okay?
Uh
when you start to follow the Bodhisattva
path
to improve yourself
and then you start doing things for
other people, in Buddhism, we call that
morality.
Okay? When you're trying to improve
yourself and you're trying to take care
of other people,
that's morality, okay?
All right. Timothy, what time I'm
supposed to shut up?
20 minutes?
Uh 8:30?
Okay, good. All right.
We finished
the perfection of ethical life.
We are going to start the perfection of
not getting upset,
okay?
Which is tough.
I I like to call it the perfection of
not getting upset. They call patience.
I I feel impatient with this word.
Uh it's not like you sit there and like
this, you know?
Uh
I don't get angry very often. My friends
know that. I you rarely see me really
angry.
Uh
but I get upset.
And and this is not talking about anger.
This is talking about upset.
Okay?
Can you keep the Bodhisattva
vow? Yes.
Did you ever get angry? Almost never.
Do ever get upset? Oh, now that's
different.
I got upset at the airport. I got upset
in the taxi. I got upset in the
restaurant. I got upset in the hotel. I
can't believe they can't clean your room
at 3:30. What's wrong What's wrong about
3:30? Anyway,
I didn't get upset. I just got a little
hot.
Okay. So, here's the next perfection,
okay? Which one Which number is it?
Number three, okay? I don't like to call
it patience. Patience to me means you
have to go to the bathroom and there
there's somebody in the bathroom and
that's patience. Yeah, not getting
upset, that's a different thing, okay?
Cuz stuff goes wrong all day.
Things happen all day long.
Can you stay cool?
And
as a Buddhist, can you stay in a good
mood
when stuff is not going well, okay? Can
you Can you laugh at yourself?
Can you have fun when when when crap is
happening?
You know, I don't know.
Like your car broke We had a nice car
breakdown, me and Stanley. That was
classic.
We're going down a very dangerous
mountain. The tire blows,
you know, and
pull over, you know, and we had fun.
You know, we weren't like "Waaah."
You know, I think we cleaned up that
mess in less than 2 minutes, right?
We were gone in 2 minutes, right? We
just left it for Edmund to do.
That's a that's a tradition in in our
group.
Okay, or Estonia.
Uh okay.
So anyway, sum of simple love to my
sipping on the what it now. This is so
beautiful. What is the essence of
Buddhist patience? There's two parts.
What is the essence of Buddhist
patience? It's two parts, okay? Uh
number one
is what we call patience in English. And
it means when somebody hurts you,
you you don't get upset, okay? When
somebody hurts you,
you don't get upset, okay? You you know,
someone does something and you're like
Okay.
You know.
And then there's a second part of
Buddhist patience, which is something I
really
I'm
I'm interested. I love Buddhism. It's so
interesting.
It's so sexy, frankly.
Uh
the second part of this perfection
is
can you be patient
with the trouble that samsara brings to
you?
Like uh
surgery, you know, some you have some
medical problem.
And the doctor's like, "Oh, we can take
care of that."
"Yeah? What do you do?" "We cut you up."
"In fact, we'll cut you up twice."
I said, "Can you just finish it the
first time?"
He's like, "You won't be able to stand
it. The pain is too much. We have to
split 50/50. We'll first of all cut you
up, then when you feel better, we'll cut
you up again."
Then um
I'm like, "Do I have a choice?" He's
like, "No."
I'm like, "Sounds good."
You know, okay. And there's a sort of a
Buddhist attitude towards
towards the pain of life, okay? If
you're alive,
you will have pain, okay? If you're
alive, the sign that you are dead is the
pain stop.
If your pain ever stop, that's
definition you're dead.
Okay?
Up to that time,
uh you have to be patient with two
things. Number one,
Okay?
I don't know how many countries there
are in the world, but there's an extra
one
called the nation of
And they're everywhere. I think they get
a free visa.
Uh
But uh nomad visa, nomad visa.
So anyway, uh
that's the first thing to be Buddhist
patient
is to be patient to people
who
who give you trouble.
That's That's only 50% of patience.
The other 50% of patience is to be
cheerful
when when they say you need two
operations, you know? By the way,
I think I can say Rob, right?
When we go in that doctor's office,
every person is happy to see us.
You know, we make them all happy. Right?
We're good at it.
Me and Rob go in there, we work on those
grumpy doctors and nurses and overworked
guys.
And nowadays when we go there for
another operation, they're like, "Hey,
good to see you, Michael. So good to see
you." I'm like, "Cut me up, honey."
You know,
you know, and we
we both know there's no choice. You have
to do it. It's a medical treatment, you
have to do it.
So, we have fun. Why not?
Okay? Why you have to be so serious
about it, you know? You don't have a
choice.
You know, you got to you got to do it.
So, why don't you
have some fun? And we have such fun. We
were having fun even in the operation
and
it was fun. The whole thing was fun.
And
Listen,
there's no reason why you have to be
unhappy when you get pain.
Because it's going to come. You cannot
stop it.
Okay? It's going to come. Everyone in
this room, I'm just the leader. I'm the
first one.
You know, you will all have this
pleasure.
And and then
have fun. Why not? You know, you can't
get out of it, you know? If you have a
human body,
things going to happen, you know? If you
live in this world,
if you own a business, if you have kids,
if you have mother,
parents, right? If if you live in a
house in a country,
on the dirt,
you're going to have pain sometimes. For
goodness sake, be cheerful.
Be happy. Okay? It's not like you have
to sit there and cut yourself with a
razor blade, okay? I'm not saying that.
Oh, I'm so happy. Guess what? I have to
accept to be happy.
You know, I'm not saying that. I'm
saying
life will bring you trouble.
The way you tell a person is a real
Buddhist is they know how to laugh at
the trouble.
You know, hey, your car broke down.
Haha, I knew it would happen.
It happened to me last week. I got a
squirrel. You know, squirrels small
animal.
Okay, he loves to eat the inside of my
car engine.
And uh
he did it like three, four times. It's
$6,000.
The the pipe of the inside the engine is
made from plastic, which is made from
peanut oil.
So he's like
Then it's like every time he does it,
it's like $5,600, you know. I'm like,
"Oh, man."
You know.
And What are you going to do, you know?
So I'm going to kill him or something.
By the way, I did catch him and I
took him to another neighbor's house.
Okay.
Uh
Okay. That's a sharing
teaching.
All right.
So Nying-ma
So we got two divisions now, right?
Number one, people cause you trouble.
That's patience, obviously. But life
cause you trouble
a Buddhist also has to be in a good mood
about it, you know.
Actually, a Buddhist you cannot tell
if the squirrel just ate their car
or if they just won the lottery, they
act the same.
Someone just gave them $10,000
or some squirrel just cost them $6,000
a real Buddhist look the same.
A real Buddhist look the same. They're
like
It happened again. What?
It happened again. With the 10,000 or
the squirrel? The squirrel.
What a wonderful Yeah.
And then what are you going to do, you
know? What?
Why be upset?
You just give yourself heart attack, you
know? It doesn't help anybody.
Okay? Got it? Now
it's perfectly logical, which is
impossible to do.
Okay.
They on I got some
I got a little bit of time. De Young
Chin Jue De.
This is beautiful. This this
Lam Rim is
I don't know. It's like
the most beautiful thing. It is really
the most beautiful thing.
You should read it every night before
you go to bed.
Ask Lindsay. De Young Chin Jue De San
Jin Mi San Nong Ka Shin.
De Da Shang Ke Yong Mi Long Choe San De
Chi Zhong Na De Na Tan Je Chong Dang Da.
in the world are countless.
There's no end.
Okay? You take care of one, three show
up.
It's like roaches. Oops.
Okay, in your house. Okay.
Uh
All right. The In your Listen from an
old man to a young people.
The old man says to the young people,
"There's a a line
of
probably a million,
that when you are born, they get in
line.
And then each year of your life, a new
one comes. A new one comes.
They will not end before you die.
Okay? You
They won't You can't fight with them.
You can try to hurt them.
You can kick them out of your house.
You can make sure they don't come back
to your country.
You can do You can try one by one
to hurt all the who who show up
in your life. You will die before you
finish.
The line is 1 million. Trust me.
There's 1 million There's still 900,000
waiting.
And for each of you,
they are waiting. Okay? Irritating
people
are there. You cannot
physically
get rid of them all before you die. You
don't have time.
Okay? If you did nothing else, if you
didn't eat dinner,
if you didn't take a shower,
you know,
if you didn't do your meditation, you
just
hurt each one by one.
They They will not run out before you
die. Okay? You will still be doing it on
the last day of your life. Okay?
Therefore,
it's more logical
to take care of your
upset first.
Okay? Don't hurt the people who hurt you
one by one.
Don't try to hurt them one by one. Hurt
your upset.
Stop your upset.
Then Then you're finished.
Then you're finished. What's the for
$1,000?
Do we have a thousand dollars? I got to
borrow.
Tomorrow I'll pay you tomorrow.
Okay?
Okay, you ready? Everyone woke up.
For $1,000,
what's the famous example by Shantideva
about trying to stop all the people who
hurt you?
There's a system. You raise your hand,
you get the microphone.
I don't just give away money.
Did I tell her that if she's wrong, she
pays me a thousand dollars?
No, I'm kidding. I'm kidding.
Uh if you can't
do uh
do with it
do something about it. If you not can do
something, just shut up.
That's a great Shantideva quotation.
Unfortunately, it's not the one I'm
looking for.
But I I honor you.
She said I'd rather have 1,000 bucks
than your honoring."
Okay. Okay.
Kim says never wrong.
Uh after he taught the last two chapter
and like he didn't tell anyone clearly.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Too complicated.
All right. Cancel the bet.
Uh don't try to cover the whole world
with leather.
Just buy some shoes, god dang it.
Okay? Got it?
You cannot stop every irritating person
in the world. You don't have Listen,
I'm an old man. I tried.
And I'm fast.
And I couldn't stop every irritating
person. They're still waiting in line.
Okay? Just stop your anger.
And then you're done. You're finished.
The rest of your life you're in a good
mood.
Okay?
Right? Okay? You cannot stop
every person who's irritating. You
cannot cover the world with leather.
Just put some shoes on.
Okay? Take care of yourself. Okay? All
right.
Okay, 500 bucks cuz it was a Shanti Deva
Kuntala.
All right.
If If you can If you can destroy your
anger, it's equal to destroying all your
enemies.
Okay? Got it? Okay.
Uh if you And in fact, if you don't
fight your anger and if you don't fight
your habit of getting upset,
if you're not in a good mood all the day
all day every day even they're cutting
you up.
Give me some more of that anesthesia.
That's good stuff.
You know,
okay.
Uh
it just gets worse and worse and worse,
okay. It just gets It doesn't work to It
stop all the
stupid people in the world and when you
try they multiply.
Okay, because that's karma. Okay.
All right.
Uh there's a thing in Sanskrit called
tapas. Say tapas.
There's two tapases. One tapas means
Spanish snacks.
I like that one.
But there's another Sanskrit tapas which
means uh
difficult spiritual practice. And in
India
in some Hindu groups
for example
you hold up your arm for 20 years
until the arm almost disappear, you
know, or you sit uh
you sit in a in a circle of fire and you
see how long you can sit there.
And then you're supposed to be some kind
of special person like that.
And and in and in Buddhism
uh
sit with an for 10 minutes, 20
minutes, whole day, marry them.
See if you can do it.
Just to see if you can do it. I think
that's what my wife did.
Uh
Just to You see, a Buddhist doesn't try
to avoid
people who bother them. A Buddhist tries
to get connected with them, okay. Well,
you you want to come work for me? Why?
Cuz I never met such an
I I need someone
who can
help me with my anger. Okay, Geshe-la.
Really? Have fun doing Buddhism. Don't
be so serious.
Oh, Geshe-la said I shouldn't get angry.
Okay.
One more picture.
No.
It's a coffin, you guys. 48.10.
Oh, there we go.
Okay.
Okay, from my heart, okay?
I just finished a new DCI level.
It's going to be in November, Geshe-la.
Advanced level four.
December.
And basically, the advanced level four
new DCI level is called how to double
your productivity.
How to do twice as much
business or or twice as much family
things, okay? How to double your life.
How to get twice as much done, okay?
And
people ask me
many people ask me, "How you get so much
things done?"
You know, how do you do that?
You know, how how do you get so much
things done, Geshe-la? I have 42
companies.
Okay? And and I run them all and I'm
happy and I'm relaxed.
Okay? They say, "How how do how do you
do it?"
Because I don't waste time with
I'm serious and I'm sorry to use bad
language, but my wife's not here, so I
can.
And nobody's going to tell her, either.
Right?
Okay. I I'll tell you the secret
to productivity. I'll tell you the
secret to success.
Don't give 1 minute of your
day.
You know, someone say something bad to
you, you're like, "Haha,
oh, cool. Thanks. Bye."
You know,
okay. Someone cheat you, you're like,
"Oh, man. I hope I never see you again.
Bye." You know, I don't fight with
people. I don't waste my time. My
friends know that. I I just
I I'm not interested.
I learned the secret to life.
I I let them go be to themself.
Which is the worst thing for an
is to spend time with themself.
You see what I mean? And I don't spend
time fighting with them. I don't fight
with anybody. Someone hurt me, I'm like,
"Okay, I'll meet you in the next life.
Don't be late."
You know, I You know, I just don't worry
about it, okay? And I really encourage
you young people
uh from an old man who who had a very
productive life.
Someone asked me, uh my lawyer asked me,
"You're getting old. You're having all
these operations.
You better tell your wife where your
stuff is."
And I'm like, "Thanks, you know." And he
says, "Like, how many books did you
write?" I said, "I don't know."
He said, "Well, can you make a list in
case you die?"
I'm like, "Okay.
It's 126
books."
Okay? And uh
And he said, "My God, how How'd you do
that?" I said, "I don't fight with
people."
I You know, when people are bad to me,
or people are not nice to me, people
complain, people want to fight with me,
I'm like
I'm sorry. I got to write another book.
I'll fight with you tomorrow. You come
back tomorrow, you know, and really,
please, okay?
And your life is so much more pleasant.
You know, someone wants to fight with
you, someone wants to cause you trouble,
then just say, "Oh, that's cool, man.
You want to got something to say? I'll
listen." Then I work, you know. While
they're complaining, I write another
book.
You know, and
okay?
Uh that's the which perfection? Third?
Third perfection. Okay, we're not quite
finished with it.
Uh we'll finish it tomorrow.
But but from my heart, okay?
This life is very precious.
And this life is very beautiful.
And don't let
don't let unhappy people ruin your day.
Okay? Just tell them, "Okay, that's
cool."
They they want to fight with you? Just
like, "That's cool, man."
Sounds good.
See you.
I got to You know, it's the ultimate
There's two ultimate methods, secret
Diamond Way. Everybody asked, "Geshe la,
can you teach Diamond Way?" Yeah.
"You want to do some Diamond Way right
now?" Yeah. "You guys ready?" Yeah.
"Someone want to cause you trouble?"
Say,
"I'll be right back. I got to go to
toilet."
Okay? No one ever stop you.
Then just don't come out of the toilet.
Like write a book in the toilet.
Okay, that's the first method.
What's the second one? Oh, this is
really cool.
If your family's having a fight on a
holiday, like the holidays are coming
up, right? Chinese New Year.
Then everybody wants to have a fight.
People drink too much.
Then Uh, if if they're fighting in the
kitchen, get a glass of water.
When the fight gets pretty serious, drop
it.
Just drop it.
There's glass everywhere. You're like,
"Everybody
stand still. Don't go Nobody move."
Then you clean up the glass, okay? And
everyone forgot to fight.
Okay, this is old man's secret method.
There I gave you diamond way, two
things. Toilet and a glass. Don't
forget.
Cause it
Okay?
Just change people's focus, okay? And
and
just distract people, okay? And and
don't waste time.
Listen.
You don't have time to get angry at
people. You will die.
You will die. I'm telling you.
I never thought I'd get old. Now I'm
old, okay? You also get old. Don't waste
your Don't give them your time.
Your time is the most precious thing you
have. Your time has no price.
Your time is worth $1 million per
minute.
Don't give it to stupid people.
Okay? Don't give it to them. Say Say, "I
I love you.
You go irritate somebody else. I'm busy.
I I I have other things to do."
Don't fight with people. It's big waste
of time. Always a waste of time, okay?
Cool.
See you tomorrow. Mingtianjian.
Okay, bye.